Hey look guys my name is Jenna welcome
back to my C++ series so today we're
gonna be talking all about precompiled
headers in C++ we're gonna first of all
start off by just talking about them
what they are and why you should be
using them and then after that we're
gonna jump into both Visual Studio and
GCC give us boss and kind of take a look
at a real world example of how to
actually set them up and see the actual
benefits in a very simple example okay
so first of all what are pre-compiled
headers I'm sure that if you've been
like using simple software any kind of
moderate amount of time you've probably
heard of them but I would place a fair
bet that a lot of you probably aren't
using them because really they're not
really required to be used there's
something that is probably quite vital
for larger projects but for most of you
who are kind of still learning you're
probably not you probably don't have
massive projects in which you would
really need to use C++ and if you
haven't actually worked somewhere or
worked on a large project than you
probably would never have really set
this up by yourself unless someone's
explicitly kind of told you hey you know
you should start using pre-compiled
headers so there's a good kind of bet
that I think a lot of you guys aren't
using them but you need to use them they
will kind of help you out so much.what
precompiled headers actually do is they
give you an opportunity to grab a bunch
of header files and convert them into
essentially a kind of compiled format
that the compiler can then use instead
of having to read those header files
over and over again so here's an example
right I use the standard template
library quite a lot right on my be using
vector might be using string we might be
using other things in the standard
library like you know STD see out all of
those kind of files right especially the
Senate template library comes from
header files right they're made out of
header files because they're templates
they have to be defined in header files
now every time that I include vector
let's just use that as an example every
time I include vector in one of my C++
files it needs to read that entire
vector header file and compile it not
only that with vector
includes a bunch of other include files
right that needs to happen as well the
preprocessor has to go in copy all of
that into that vector file essentially
you end up with something that's
probably around a hundred thousand lines
of code or so that needs to be parsed
tokenized and compiled in some form
before you actually get into your main
kind of file that you're trying to
compile because if your main file
includes vector then vector has to be
copied and pasted into that main file
and then that whole kind of conglomerate
of code that whole massive code has to
be parsed and compiled every time if you
suddenly decide I'm going to change my
main kind of file that I'm trying to
compile a little bit and my main file I
just mean a C++ file right it's just the
one that what I'm working on right now
because if you have us if you have many
stable Clause files in your project many
places that include a vector obviously
they're going to be individually
included in every single file right
because that's how the compiler works
every translation unit is compiled
separately and then later the link kind
of links all that together if you're
unfamiliar with that definitely check
out the video on how an astable sauce
works and how the compiler works and how
link works all that fun stuff anyway the
point is every time you make a change in
that people to save us loss file the
whole thing has to be written filed
right so that vector class all that's
part of that vector file has to be
copied and pasted into your staples last
file paused all over again from scratch
and compiled again because you've got a
nerve added a blank line or something
like that right what that means is that
your compile times are going to be a lot
longer than they potentially could be
not only that but think about the fact
of you have multiple fields they both
loss files in your project they all
include vector right well suddenly you
have to keep pausing that same code all
over again every single time for each
translation unit for each CPP file that
you're actually trying to compile that
takes time so what you can do instead is
use something called a precompiled
header what that does is it takes a
bunch of header files which you tell it
to take in write a bunch of code
essentially and it compiles it once and
it stores it in a binary format that is
way faster for the compiler to actually
deal with that in just
texts because already in a past kind of
state it's in binary not text right
that's ready to go
and every time you include that pregnant
Pal pedophile it already has everything
you need that's it right so instead of
it pausing that entire back to file
every single time it only needs to look
at the precompiled header which is
already in a great fast easy to use
binary format is it used for the
compiled letters binary format right
which it just takes every time you need
vector because you've included your
break and pulse header in your source
file that you're currently compiling and
all the dot is there and what that means
is that it results in way way way faster
compilation times okay your projects
will be compiled like many times faster
because of this especially as you're
kind of as you're kind of project size I
guess
grows and you end up having more and
more stable fluff files more and more
header files all of that stuff and you
can keep shopping in more stuff into the
break above header and also you have
more source files which make compiling
that use common headers it's just gonna
be exponentially faster it's gonna be so
much better so you need to need to need
to use precompiled headers if you care
about compilation times if you say that
your compilation times are getting out
of hand and it's taking like a minute to
compile you can potentially reduce that
to like eight seconds if you just kind
of start using precompiled headers
okay so I've talked about the greatness
of breaking fault headers and we're
gonna go ahead and take a look at an
example in a minute but I also want to
talk about what not to do with break
compiled headers so what I've mentioned
so far kind of as to what a precompiled
header actually is it is essentially a
header file which includes a bunch of
other header files right so because of
that a lot of people might be like okay
well I can just put everything in my
project into that PCH into that
precompiled header and if I do that then
we'll all get really fast build times
right well yes but but if you put stuff
in your break apart header which changes
so stuff in your actual project that
you're likely to change because you're
working on your project obviously the
precompiled header has to be rebuilt and
that takes time right that could
potentially end up slowing down your
compilation so do not put frequently
changing files into that preg
hello really what it should be useful
there's nothing wrong with you putting
kind of your own project files into
there like if I have something like a
log H file which doesn't really change
because how often do I touch my own
logging library right I kind of read
written that once it's not like I have
to keep adding stuff to it that's fine
you can put that into your breaker
bulkhead up because that's something
that first of all is needed a lot right
which also makes it convenient to use
because since you're including your
precompiled header in every single
source file now right you also have
access to those logging functions so
that's really kind of easy to use now
now it's kind of it makes it more
convenient because you don't need to
manually include log in every single
safety big file that you have in your
project cuz you're including the
precompiled header which includes log so
that's good because it adds convenience
right but also I've made sure that I'm
not doing it if I'm going to be changing
if I'm currently working on my logging
library probably shouldn't be in the
compiled cattle and then in the protocol
header right because every time I change
that that loved our H header file it
needs to get recompiled into the written
vault header which means the whole route
to help bring compiled header I might
have said Reichenbach header the whole
precompiled header has to be rebuilt
from scratch every single time so don't
put stuff like that in it what it's
really used for is probably like
external I would say sternal
dependencies or there's a bit of an
issue with dependencies which as we'll
talk about in a minute but essentially
it's used for it's vitally used for code
that isn't yours so for example the SCL
write code that is in the standard
template library or in the standard kind
of C++ library or like the windows API
like if you want include Windows dot H
that is a massive header file which
includes a billion other header files
right you are not going to be modifying
windows at H you're not going to be
modifying the standard template library
right so there is no reason for it to
kind of not be in a precompiled header
file right it should be there because
that is a lot of code probably many
times more code than your actual
application right and when you think
about it what's your application made
out of say for fluff libraries standard
template library windows API calls that
kind of stuff right
that's what it's made out of he uses
that stuff all the time and and that's
part of that you'll never
be touching so put all of that into your
pre-compiled header right that stuff
belongs there because that is a lot of
code probably many times more code than
your actual application than your actual
project right you're compiling that
every single time per CPP file that's
terrible
put it into a program bolt head up where
it can just be left alone and you'll get
the benefit of first of all getting
access to everything in every city of a
file right you won't need to actually
include like memory for example if you
want to use smart pointers or include a
vector all the time because it's gonna
be in the PCH which will be included in
there in every single say plus plus file
that you actually ride so you'll have
access to that it's convenient and it
will speed everything up really quickly
now I decide something about
dependencies one thing that the PCH can
actually do is because you shove
everything into your PCH it can
potentially hide what's actually being
used now it's theoretically speaking me
if I write asleep but if I write a CPP
file that uses like I don't know a
window library or something right and I
put that window in library into the into
my PCH it's not really apparently clear
if you read that CPP file you don't
actually know what it needs it might
need J love W my windowing library it
might not need it might need like some
other dependencies but because all of
your dependencies are in the PCH if you
just isolate that CPP file and you take
it you don't actually know what it needs
and it can be very difficult until meant
in terms of mod like modularity and code
reuse for you to actually be like okay
well now I can take this file put into
another project wait I have no idea what
it needs right if you just had include
jail FW or something in that actual
header file and in your actual or CPP
file that you've taken you'll be very
clear wouldn't it the this file needs
this file right but if you have just
include PCH and then a bunch of includes
in that PCH it can kind of make it a
little bit harder so that's what a lot
of people kind of mention when you when
they're dealing with people
that is that you know be careful maybe
don't include all dependencies there
because it'll make it clearer and easy
to read if you actually include your
dependencies per kind of file that needs
them and I agree with that to an extent
depends how kind of specific that
dependency is if you're making a game
engine and you want to include yourself
w you know in your PC age I mean you can
but on the other hand think about how
many actual source files need that not
that many right
probably like if you've written a game
engine quite unquote properly probably
only one CPP file actually needs to
include gels W right because everything
else will kind of be abstracted and in
your own API so in that case well you
know why put gel W to your break apart
header you can so if I make anything
worse right probably however it does
probably have readability a bit and also
you'll it'll be extra stuff for your
pre-compile tether to compile that
really only one CPP file means stuff
that you should put in there as I
mentioned is like STL right because
strings or vectors or standard sea out
might be something that you that you
broadly want in a lot of places right
and stuff that you don't want to keep
breaking poly from scratch every time
gelid lb on the other hand you know kind
of something you've probably compiled
once and you're done so that's kind of
the idea of breaking belt headers I've
talked a lot about this whole thing
let's jump into it and take a look at a
few examples and we'll also kind of
measure how long it takes to build using
pre-compiled headers and not eating
precompiled headers so what we've kind
of got here is a very simple hello world
application it says hello world right
however it includes this file which i've
named pc HH now freaking bath header is
kind of what I've called it can be
called absolutely anything Visual Studio
by default makes something called STD AF
X dot H if you kind of use the C++
wizard to actually create a project or
you kind of create a project from a
template I usually create empty projects
which doesn't have any of that but um
this file can be called anything you
want it to be called and right now even
though it's called PC H bridge don't be
fooled we're not using precompiled
headers in this project what I'm doing
is I'm simply including in my in my PC H
I've just got a header file which
includes a bunch of other header files
and includes some basic kind of save
applause library stuff it includes some
other structures as well as the windows
API some windows on H right this is a
lot of code right I probably don't need
to tell you that it's a lot of code if I
just for fun go ahead and say give me
the preprocessor output so if I go to
preprocessor and then pre press s to a
file if I shut that on and then I just
hit control f7 to build this file and I
take a look at what is actually in this
main dot I file if we scroll down to the
very bottom you can see that I mean
here's our kind of see up hello world
it's like three hundred and seventy
thousand lines of code that's a lot of
stuff right that is what will be
recompiled every single time you include
this in your actual CPP files right in
every single CPP file individually it
has to go over and process three hundred
and seventy thousand lines of source
code and then tokenize them and then
compile them and then do all of that
stuff right every single time we want to
avoid that so what we can do is actually
use frigging part headers so I can turn
this into a break and path header this
is a good this is a pretty good example
of what you might have in your PC age
right I haven't got any kind of I mean
this is just a this is just a hello
world program so of course I don't have
my own kind of massive set of code but
really I'm just including stuff that I
know I'll never touch and stuff that is
likely going to be needed by this kind
of program so what I'm going to do is
first of all once you have your header
file make a CPP file which includes your
header file this is visual studios way
of doing things we're gonna take a look
at what J plus plus actually needs and a
clang is a very similar similar to GCC
as well but what we need to do for
Visual Studio is actually create a CPP
file which includes our header file
right and then on that CPP file we need
to right-click hit properties and then
go on disable saves
under safes under say a bus bus we need
to go to precompiled headers and then
select outbreak and palette header to be
create right so for this specific PCH
dot CPP file we're going to create a
precompiled header and then hit OK then
I'm going to go to the entire properties
for the entire project right the
property
for the entire project and I'm going to
and I'm going to on the safe sickles
Wells precompiled headers select this to
be used so our entire project now uses
precompiled headers and then the brigham
Bob header file that we will use will be
of course PC H dot H ok hit OK now this
of course will apply it to everything so
if I now look at the properties for main
dot CPP as an example you can see it's
set to use a program called headers and
then it includes and then a specifies
which one is used and then this is what
it will actually compile to right this
is the output file this is the compiled
binary format of our actual pre-compiled
header and then because we've set that
for the project it applies to everything
so in summary set the project who used
your precompiled headers and specify
which one is used and then for your CPP
file which includes PC H or H set it to
create precompiled header and that's all
you need to do ok so now if I just right
click build you can see we should build
successfully and everything should be
fine that's how we create PC ages now
let's take a look at how how much that
actually sped up at compile time now
keep in mind this is a very basic
project which should be even more kind
of impactful because you can see that we
really don't have anything here we've
only got one CPP file even but if we
right click go to properties and then
just disable this for now so not using
precompiled headers will kind of get an
easy kind of comparison to the before
state so what I'll do is under tools
options and the projects and solutions
vegetables as project settings I'm gonna
set build timing to yes just so that it
times how long our build takes and then
I'm just gonna clean this and then build
it and we'll take a look at how long
that takes
ok so that actually failed because conop
and main dodo BJ for some reason I'm
just gonna go to properties and make
sure because I did the preprocessor to
pre-process to a file I'll just make
sure that's set to no and then I'm going
to clean this project and then I'm going
to build the project ok so you can see
building the project a clean build took
three point three seconds right and then
if I edit the source file for example if
print HelloWorld twice and I build that
again you can see that a subsequent
build takes about one and a half seconds
right let's just do that again just for
fun to make sure that we get a more
reliable timing there we go one and a
half seconds right okay cool
so now let's just switch this let's just
switch this precompiled headers thing to
use and then I'm going to again clean it
we're gonna see how long a clean build
it takes okay about two seconds so
that's I mean it was three point three
seconds before so that's considerably
faster and now let's edit this source
file and just duplicate that line look
at that half a second okay sit down from
one-and-a-half seconds to have a second
that's three times faster I'm gonna
remove this and try it again just to
make sure and there you go
you can see just how much faster using
precompiled headers actually made this
compilation and this project is
absolutely tiny cool so let's take a
look at how we might do this in G+
Boston will also kind of time that so
the first thing I'll do is understand
the source directory here which has
these three files all I'm going to do
first of all is just see how long it
takes to compile this project without
using frequent alt headers so if I just
go ahead and write time T plus Boston
and we're using C++ 11 for this and then
just mean does he be I'll try and
compile that see how long it takes
there we go 1.5 seconds I'll go and like
modify the source file again by just
adding another line and then we'll see
how long this takes
okay about one-and-a-half seconds right
cool so now let's go ahead and actually
create a precompiled header so i do that
by basically just compiling that pc a
shot h file that's all you need to do in
GCC so i'll hit enter you can see it
takes a little bit of time and then what
it generates is this PC H or H dot g CH
net festival look at how big it is 114
megabytes that's quite large
second of all der let's go ahead and
order late a WC just so it's basically a
clean build and then we'll go ahead and
run this again look at that point two
eight seconds right if I go ahead and
remove this again and do another
compilation let's
I just do a clean thing here 0.2 seconds
right about 0.3 seconds let's just round
up you can see that is down from 1.5
seconds 2.3 seconds so much fuss that's
like five times faster okay so hopefully
all these examples have kind of shed
some light on to why you should be using
precompiled headers they speed up your
build times a lot and they also make it
more convenient to actually write code
since you don't have to keep including
commonly used header files over and over
again I hope that made sense let me know
in the comments below if you've been
using precompiled headers that this is
the first time you've heard of it if you
think that this is something that you
should use or kind of your experience
with them in general I every software
project should be using precompiled
headers there's no real kind of should I
use them should I not every predator
should be using them what to put into
your breaking ball Petter has a
different story and we've covered a few
of the kind of good examples of what you
should put in there but whether or not
you should be using them yes absolutely
unless you're making a little sandbox
project and you don't want to go through
the hassle of setting it up not that
it's particularly hard then yeah I
probably would avoid that but otherwise
you should be using for compile tez hope
you guys enjoy this video if you did you
can hit the like button you can help
support this series and everything that
I do here on this channel by going to
pee I'm not home for the churner you get
videos early as well as access to cool
kind of source software development
repositories and many other cool rewards
and it does help me make more of these
videos I hope you guys enjoyed this
leave some comments below as to what you
want to see next
in the staples loss series I'll probably
be kind of since I'm focusing a lot on
the game engine series I'll be kind of
making videos to do with that probably
standalone Sables loss videos based on
topics that we cover there but also that
game engine series is a really good
example to see all of these kind of
concepts that we've been learning in
this again the staples boss series
actually come together so definitely
check that out I will see you guys next
time goodbye
[Music]